MELISSA E. BASSETT, CPLP

PO Box 4039 Portsmouth, NH 03802 603-686-9875

MEBassey@Comcast.net http://www.linkedin.com/in/melissabassettcplp

PROFILE

Certified Professional in Learning and Performance (CPLP) with 22 years of experience including advanced instructional design and development, training function management, and human performance improvement. Extensive e-learning design, project management, and evaluation experience. Performance improvement interventions resulting in reduced costs, improved job performance, enhanced communications, desired behavior change, and improved safety performance. Top performance and satisfaction ratings from clients, managers, and colleagues. *Demonstrated knowledge and skill areas include:*

- Rapid eLearning Design/Development
- Blended Learning Design/Development
- Measurement/Assessment/Evaluation
- Learning Function Management
- Multiple Projects Management
- Learning Management System

- Communication/Presentation
- Multimedia/Writing Creativity
- Technical/Procedure Writing
- Editing
- Human Performance Improvement
- Consulting/Mentoring

KEY ACCOMPLISHMENTS

- Significantly contributed to the Oak Ridge National Laboratory (ORNL) workplace learning and performance activities cited in the applications that won the international 2007 and 2008 American Society for Training and Development (ASTD) BEST Awards and the 2007, 2008, and 2009 *Training* Top 125 Awards.
- Designed, implemented, and/or managed numerous performance improvement interventions at ORNL that contributed to the improved maturity of the Training and Qualification Management System (TQMS).
- Co-designed and developed three of five original courses for the ASTD Human Performance Improvement (HPI) Certificate Program. The three topical areas are selecting interventions, evaluating interventions, and transitioning to performance improvement.
- Designed and developed management level courses for the Tennessee Valley Authority University (TVAU). These courses were acknowledged as key contributors to the corporate university's receipt of a national award.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

OAK RIDGE NATIONAL LABORATORY

Jun 2002 to Sep 2011

Oak Ridge, TN

Senior Instructional Designer / Performance Improvement Consultant

As a full-time, staff augmentation subcontractor, I supported the Department of Energy's (DOE) Oak Ridge National Laboratory (ORNL) managed by UT-Battelle, LLC.

- Designed, developed, and evaluated online and classroom delivery of environmental, safety, health, and quality learning content to meet DOE, federal, state, and local compliance requirements
- Designed more than 30 learning and development programs including online courses for laboratory-wide completion (8000 ORNL staff members)
- Conducted an in-depth investigation of best practices in web-based instruction and formulated a three-year plan to improve online and blended instruction at ORNL
- Designed and conducted self-assessments of the ORNL Training and Qualification Management System and Training Services, analyzed the results, and recommended improvement solutions
- Implemented and evaluated performance improvement solutions
- Wrote technical reports and develop surveys
- Crafted the Training Organization's internal operating procedures that guide instructional systems design (ISD) at ORNL

PINNACLE PERFORMANCE PARTNERS

Jul 1998 - Jun 2002

Knoxville, TN

Co-owner / Performance Improvement Consultant

- Co-founded and operated a learning and performance business specializing in performance improvement consulting and customized instructional design, development, and delivery.
 Performed all areas of business operations and management including business development, marketing, advertising, billing, and accounting
- Partial list of clients includes ASTD; Fort Campbell Army Base; ImagePoint; The University of Tennessee

MELIMAX Apr 1994 – Jun 1998

Knoxville, TN

Owner / Senior Instructional Designer

- Founded and operated a learning business specializing in customized instructional design, development, and delivery. Drove all sales, managed client relationships, and performed needs analysis, program design, materials development, training delivery, and evaluation
- Partial list of clients includes John Deere; the Department of Energy; Regal Cinemas; Tennessee
 Valley Authority; Union Planters Bank

ALUMINUM COMPANY OF AMERICA

Sep 1989 - Mar 1994

Alcoa, TN

Instructional Design Specialist

 Designed, developed, and delivered technical and non-technical training and education programs in support of the Tennessee Operations' \$450 million modernization

KNOX COUNTY SCHOOL SYSTEM

Aug 1980 - Aug 1989

Knoxville, TN

Special Education Teacher

- Taught elementary, middle, and high school level students with special learning needs
- Conducted diagnostic assessments and implemented individual education programs
- Also certified in elementary education and elementary guidance counseling

EDUCATION

Master of Science

Educational Psychology

The University of Tennessee Knoxville, TN

Bachelor of Science, magna cum laude

Education

The University of Tennessee Knoxville, TN

PROFESSIONAL DEVELOPMENT / TRAINING

Certified Professional in Learning and Performance (CPLP)

American Society for Training and Development (ASTD) Certification Institute

ASTD E-Learning Instructional Design Certificate

Allen Interactions

Robert Mager's Criterion-Referenced Instruction and Instructional Module Development

Center for Effective Performance

APPLICATIONS

Articulate, Microsoft Office

PROFESSIONAL MEMBERSHIPS

American Society for Training and Development (ASTD) - International